Guide to the Robinson Jeffers Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robinson Jeffers collection
1920-1951
1920-1933
YCAL MSS 284
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.67
(5 boxes)
The collection consists of manuscripts of Robinson Jeffers's poetry and a small amount of correspondence and other papers related to Jeffers.
Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase, 194951-2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Photographs of Robinson Jeffers (Za J355 +G1), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Pamphlets by and about Robinson Jeffers, including newspaper clippings and other ephemera (Za J355 +1), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available for portions of the John Hay Whitney Gift including Autograph manuscript of "Cawdor" (Film #2777) and Manuscripts of "Roan stallion," "The tower beyond tragedy," and an unpublished poem (Film #903)
Robinson Jeffers
Robinson Jeffers (1887-1962) was born John Robinson Jeffers in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, the son of the Reverend Dr. William Hamilton Jeffers and Annie Robinson Tuttle. He was educated by his father and at European boarding schools. In 1902, Jeffers entered the University of Western Pennsylvania (now the University of Pittsburgh), but was graduated from Occidental College, California, three years later. He pursued graduate studies in literature and philosophy at the Universities of Southern California and Zurich, before enrolling in the Medical School at the University of Southern California in September 1907. In 1910 he left medical school to study forestry for one year at the University of Washington.
While studying at the University of Southern California, Jeffers met Una Call Kuster, the wife of a prominent Los Angeles attorney. Their involvement and Kuster's ensuing divorce was a public scandal that was widely reported. Jeffers and Kuster were married in 1913 and one year later settled in Carmel, California where Jeffers eventually built the stone cottage and tower he called "Tor House." A daughter was born in 1914 but died in infancy; twin sons were born in 1916. In 1912 Jeffers privately published his first volume of poetry, Flagons and Apples. In 1916 his second volume, Californians, was commercially published. Tamar and Other Poems (1924), his third volume, proved both a formal and critical breakthrough and was reissued in an expanded edition the following year under the title Roan Stallion, Tamar and other Poems. Over a period encompassing five decades, Jeffers published nearly two-dozen volumes of poetry. In 1954 he published his last volume, Hungerfield and Other Poems, an expanded edition of his Hungerfield (1952) which included a eulogy for Una Jeffers who died in 1950. A volume of Jeffers' uncollected poems, The Beginning and the End and Other Poems, was published posthumously in 1963.
Scope and Contents
The Robinson Jeffers Collection encompasses accessions of single manuscripts, small groups of manuscripts, and other papers pertaining to Robinson Jeffers, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into this collection have been organized into three series documenting the gifts of John Hay Whitney, Robert M. Leylan, and materials from other sources. The collection spans the years 1922-1951, with the bulk of material dating from 1922-1933.
The bulk of the collection consists of manuscript drafts of Jeffers' early narrative and lyrical poems. The John Hay Whitney Gift materials contain significant annotation and are inscribed with descriptive and analytical commentary. Additionally, a single folded sheet labeled "Genesis of Tamar," includes plans for the stairway of the tower at Tor House. The Robert M. Leylan Gift includes full drafts of shorter poems and passages from longer and unidentified poems. The third series, Materials from Other Sources, incorporates a typescript copy of a study of the poetry of Robinson Jeffers by Howard Trivers and annotated by Robert M. Leylan.
The limited correspondence in each series includes letters from Robinson and Una Jeffers, the book dealer Barnet B. Ruder, and the Jeffers bibliographer S. S. Alberts, concerning the various manuscript materials.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. John Hay Whitney Gift, II. Robert M. Leylan Gift, III. Materials from Other Sources. IV. 2004 Addition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Poets, American; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962
- John Hay Whitney Gift, 1922-1951, undated; Series I; (4 boxes)
  Custodial History
  Gift of John Hay Whitney, 1951.
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Writings and Correspondence.
  - Writings, 1922-1933
    Scope and Contents
    The writings consist of bound volumes of manuscripts of Jeffers' poems. The file titles were transcribed directly from the spines of the volumes. One volume, "Manuscript Poems" consists of multiple shorter works by Jeffers.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of the poem.
    - "Cawdor", 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Original manuscript written in pencil on 137 numbered leaves, 28 cm.; inscribed on the first and last leaves by the author; with a long autograph inscription concerning the poem, signed and dated January 1929, on a separate leaf, and with an autograph letter signed from Una (Mrs. Robinson) Jeffers to Barnet B. Ruder concerning the manuscript, January 15, 1929, laid in.
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Film #2777
    - "Dear Judas"; "The Loving Shepherdess", 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Dear Judas", 1928-1930
        Original manuscript, written in pencil on 40 numbered leaves, plus 2 pages numbered 41 and 42, 28 cm.; with an autograph inscription concerning the poem, signed and dated September 8, 1930, on a separate leaf.
      - "The Loving Shepherdess", 1929-1930
        Original manuscript, written in pencil on 64 numbered leaves, 28 cm.; with an autograph inscription concerning the poem, signed and dated September 8, 1930, on a separate leaf.
    - "Descent to the Dead", 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Original manuscript, written in pencil on 25 numbered leaves (some leaves written on both sides and on verso of letters) plus 1 leaf of index, 28 cm.; with an autograph inscription concerning the poems, signed and dated April 27, 1932, on a separate leaf.
    - Give Your Heart to the Hawks and Other Poems, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Original manuscript, written chiefly in pencil on 254 leaves (some written on both sides), 28 cm.; with an autograph inscription concerning the manuscript and dated December 1933.
    - Manuscript poems, circa 1927, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - "Ascent to the Sierras" and "The Summit Redwood", undated
        Original manuscript,written in pencil on 2 leaves, 28 cm; inscribed,"Original manuscript of 'Ascent to the Sierras.' Robinson Jeffers," with verso inscription,"Original manuscript of 'The Summit Redwood.' Robinson Jeffers."
      - "Ascent to the Sierras", undated
        Original typescript, with manuscript corrections, on 2 leaves, 28 cm.; inscribed "Second draft. Robinson Jeffers."
      - "The Bird with the Dark Plumes", undated
        Original manuscript, written in pencil on 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Original manuscript of 'The Bird with the Dark Plumes.' Robinson Jeffers."
      - "Bixby's Landing", undated
        Original manuscript, written in pencil on 2 leaves, 17x22 cm.; inscribed "Original manuscript of 'Bixby's Landing.'... Robinson Jeffers."
      - "Contrast", undated
        Original typescript with manuscript corrections in pencil, 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Second draft, Robinson Jeffers."
      - "Fawn's Foster Mother", undated
        Original typescript, with manuscript corrections in pencil, 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Second draft. Robinson Jeffers." Cancelled title: "The woman who nursed a fawn."
      - "Meditation on Saviors", undated
        Original manuscript, written in pencil on 7 leaves, 28 cm. (leaf 6, 18x25 cm.); inscribed "Original manuscript of 'Meditation on saviors.' Robinson Jeffers." Versos of leaves 1, 4, 5, and 6 have manuscript notes and drafts.
      - "Meditation on Saviors", undated
        Original typescript, on 7 leaves, 28 cm.; inscribed "Second draft of 'Medtation on Saviors.' Robinson Jeffers." Cancelled titles: "Commentary on the women at Point Sur," "The peace or the people," and "Meditation on Redeemers."
      - "Ocean", undated
        Original typescript with manuscript corrections in pencil, 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Second draft. Robinson Jeffers."
      - "A Redeemer", circa 1927
        Original manuscript, written in pencil, on 5 leaves, 16-28 cm.; inscribed "'A Redeemer.... Robinson Jeffers."
      - "A Redeemer", undated
        Original typescript, with minor manuscript corrections in pencil, 4 leaves, 28 cm.
      - "Soliloquy", undated
        Original typescipt, with manuscript corrections in pencil, 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Revised second draught of 'Soliloquy.' Robinson Jeffers."
      - "The Summit Redwood", undated
        Original typescript, with corrections in pencil, 2 leaves, 28 cm.; inscribed "(Second draft.) Robinson Jeffers."
      - "To a Young Artist", circa 1927
        Original manuscript on 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Original manuscript of 'To a Young Artist.' Robinson Jeffers." Written on verso, beginning of an autograph letter addressed "Dear Ben," Carmel, California, July 1, 1927.
      - "Tor House", undated
        Original typescript, with manuscript corrections in pencil, 1 leaf, 28 cm.; inscribed "Second draft. Robinson Jeffers."
    - "Roan Stallion," "The Tower Beyond Tragedy," & an unpublished poem, 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Film 903
      - "Roan Stallion", 1925
        Original manuscript, [19] pages, 27.5x33 cm.; pages [5]-[19] are written on versos of leaves numbered 54, 84-85, 90-93, 99-101, 118-119, and 120-122 of typewritten manuscript of a long narrative poem on Christ by Jeffers. Inscribed: "First draught of 'Roan Stallion' May-June 1925. R. J."
      - "The Tower Beyond Tragedy", 1924-1925
        Original manuscript, [55] pages, 15.5x33; written in part on versos of discarded business letters, leaves numbered 87-89, 113-194, and 216-227 of typewritten manuscript of a long narrative poem on Christ by Jeffers, and on other leaves of discarded typescript. Inscribed: "First draught of 'The Tower Beyond Tragedy,' 1924-1925. R. J."
    - Roan Stallion, Tamar, and Other Poems, [1925?] (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Galley proofs, with manuscript corrections, 73 leaves; page proofs, with manuscript corrections, 81 leaves; pages (13-127) clipped from a copy of Tamar and other poems ([1924]), from which galleys 29-73 were set.
    - Genesis of "Tamar", [after 1922 Feb 22]-1925 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - "Tamar", [after 1922 Feb 22]
        Original manuscript, written in pencil, 1 leaf, 36x63 (folded); contains the first germ of the Tamar story, with notes for its expansion; original manuscript of first and final draft of the poem 'Continent's end' from the Tamar volume; original manuscripts of fragments of two other short poems, never finished; and plans for the stairway of the granite tower which Jeffers built beside his house. Written on verso of Los Angeles Trust & Savings Bank statement dated January 17, 1922 to February 17, 1922.
      - Correspondence, 1925 Nov 25
        Robinson Jeffers, typed letter signed to Donald Friede, 1 leaf (28 cm.), inscribed Carmel, California
    - "Tamar" (negative copy), after 1922 Feb 22 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Thurso's Landing and Other Poems, before 1932 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Original manuscript, 195 numbered leaves, plus 1 leaf of index, 28 cm.; with an autograph inscription concerning the manuscript, signed and dated April 27, 1932.
    - The Women at Point Sur
      - Original manuscript, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        131 numbered leaves, 28 cm.; inscribed by the author to Donald Friede, with a note concerning the manuscript.
      - Galley proofs and page proofs, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 12)
        Galley proofs, 45 leaves, and page proofs, 55 leaves, with manuscript corrections.
  - Correspondence, 1951 May 24 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Robinson Jeffers, autograph letter signed to John Hay Whitney, 1 leaf (28 cm.), inscribed Tor House, Carmel, California
- Robert M. Leylan Gift, 1929-1932; Series II; 7
  Gift of Robert M. Leylan, 1950 and, 1966.
  - Writings, 1929-1932, undated
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    Includes autograph and typescript copies of manuscripts of Jeffers' poetry.
    - "Birds", undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Autograph manuscript: [2] pages, 14.5 cm. With positive photostat.
    - "The Broken Balance", before 1929 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Original manuscript, 1 leaf, 28 cm.; from Section IV of the poem. Published in Dear Judas and Other Poems (1929). With positive photostat.
      Received laid in to limited edition of S. S. Alberts, A Bibliography of the Works of Robinson Jeffers (1933).
    - "Day After To-morrow", undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Original typescript, with manuscript corrections in pencil, 1 leaf, 28 cm. With positive photostat.
    - "Hands", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Autograph manuscript, 1 leaf, 27 cm. Original title: "The Cave of Hands." With positive photostat.
    - "Hooded Night", undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Autograph manuscript, [1] page, 28 cm. On verso, original manuscript verses discarded from his "Cawdor." With positive photostat.
    - [Poems], undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Original manuscripts (positive photostats), 10 leaves, 28 cm.; includes poems entitled "The enemy," "Post mortem," "Credo," "Day after to-morrow," passages from "Cawdor," and other unidentified poems. (Originals written on both sides of 5 leaves.)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1932 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    3 letters addressed to Robert M. Levy concerning manuscripts of Robinson Jeffers. S. S. Alberts, typed letter signed, 1 leaf (27 cm.), with original envelope; dated 1932 Dec 28. Una Jeffers, autograph letter signed, 1 leaf (29.5 cm.), with original envelope; dated 1929 Feb 17. Barnet Ruder, typed letter signed, 2 leaves (22.5 cm), with original envelope, dated 1929 Feb 25.
- Materials from Other Sources, 1929-1930; Series III; 2
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders.
  - Correspondence, 1929 Apr 17 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    2 letters addressed to Dudley Nichols. Robinson Jeffers, autograph letter signed, 2 pages (28 cm.), 1929 Apr 17. Enclosure: Una Jeffers, autograph letter signed, 1 page (30 cm.), 1929 Apr 17. With original envelope.
    Gift of Dudley Nichols, 1949
  - Writings by other authors: Trivers, Howard, "Robinson Jeffers: A Study", 1929-1930 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Typescript (carbon): 26, [4] leaves, 28 cm. Signed by the author on leaf 26. With manuscript comments by Robert M. Leylan.
- 2004 Addition, 1920-1928; 0.21; (1 box)
  - "Ante Mortem," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - "Apology for Bad Dreams," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1925, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "Birth Dues," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - "Dead Man's Child," drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, 1928, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - "The Machine," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - "Natural Music," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - "On Building With Stone," draft, typescript, corrected, [1928?] (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - "To the Children," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - "To the House," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1920, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - "To the Rock That Will Be the Corner-stone of the House," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, 1923, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - "The Trumpet," draft, autograph manuscript, corrected, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)